Inventory of the Larry Jay Diamond clippings collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Larry Jay Diamond clippings collection
1978-2004
2002C79
Diamond, Larry Jay, collector.
11 manuscript boxes (4.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Relates to political, social and economic conditions in Nigeria.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2002.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
Larry Diamond is a senior fellow at the Hoover Institution and the Freeman Spogli Institute for International Studies, where he directs the Center on Democracy, Development, and the Rule of Law. He is the founding co-editor of the Journal of Democracy and serves as senior consultant at the International Forum for Democratic Studies of the National Endowment for Democracy. With Abbas Milani, he coordinates the Hoover Institution Project on Democracy in Iran. His research focuses on comparative trends in the stability of democracy in developing countries and post communist states and on US foreign policy. At Stanford University, he is a professor by courtesy of political science and sociology.
Diamond has edited or co-edited more than 30 books on democracy, including the recent titles How People View Democracy, How East Asians View Democracy, Latin America's Struggle for Democracy, Political Change in China: Comparisons with Taiwan, and Assessing the Quality of Democracy. Among his other published works are, Developing Democracy: Toward Consolidation (1999), Promoting Democracy in the 1990s (1995), and Class, Ethnicity, and Democracy in Nigeria (1989).
Source: http://www.stanford.edu/~ldiamond/
Scope and Content of Collection
Acquired in 2002, the Larry Jay Diamond collection in the Hoover Institution Archives includes clippings, correspondence, writings, conference proceedings, and printed matter relating to political, social and economic conditions before, during, and after Presidential elections in Nigeria in 1983.
Research materials in the papers pertain to Diamond's book Class, Ethnicity, and Democracy in Nigeria (1989). There are draft chapters of the book on the floppy disks.
The papers include materials relating to his teaching activities as a Fulbright visiting lecturer at Bayero University Kano (BUK), Nigeria, from 1982 to 1983, as well as conference proceedings of National United Power Convention (NUPC) in Baghdad in 2004.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Nigeria.
Collection Contents
- Clippings on Nigerian politics, 1978-1992. (Box 1-11)
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Agriculture, 1979-1983 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Alhaji Moshood Abiola, 1983 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Aliens control, 1983 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Assessments of democracy in Nigeria, 1983 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Auto accidents, 1990 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Biographies, profiles, and leaders, 1982-1983 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Business and finance, 1990 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Campaign obstruction, 1983 (Folder 1: 7-9)
  - Campaign pledges and speeches, 1982-1983 (Folder 1: 10-12)
  - Census, 1990 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Chief Emeka Ojukwu, 1983 (Folder 1: 14)
  - Constitution as political structure, 1983 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Corruption and accountability, 1981-1992 (Folder 2: 1-4)
  - Cultural and social problems, 1981-1983 (Folder 2: 5)
  - Development of class structure, 1981-1983 (Folder 2: 6)
  - Drug trade, international, 1990 (Folder 2: 7)
  - Economic development, 1982-1983 (Folder 2: 8-10)
  - Education, 1990 (Folder 2: 11)
  - Election prospects, 1982-1983 (Folder 2: 12)
  - Electoral administration, Federal Electoral Commission (FEDECO), 1982-1983 (Folder 2: 13-14)
  - Ethnics, 1982-1983 (Folder 3: 1-2)
  - Ethnicity, 1990 (Folder 3: 3)
  - External debt, 1990 (Folder 3: 4)
  - First Lady of Nigeria, Better Life Fair, 1990 (Folder 3: 5)
  - Foreign affairs, 1983 (Folder 3: 6-7)
  - Human rights; justice, 1990 (Folder 3: 8)
  - Igbos and politics, 1983 (Folder 3: 9)
  - International business, 1990 (Folder 3: 10)
  - International drug trade, 1990 (Folder 3: 11)
  - Interviews with leaders, 1983 (Folder 3: 12)
  - Islam, 1983 (Folder 3: 13)
  - Judiciary, 1983-1984 (Folder 3: 14)
  - Labor trade unions, 1983 (Folder 3: 15)
  - Languages, official and spoken, 1990 (Folder 3: 16)
  - Law: judiciary, 1990 (Folder 3: 17)
  - Legitimacy, 1982-1983 (Folder 3: 18)
  - Local government, 1983-1990 (Folder 3: 19-20)
  - Magazine articles, 1982-1983 (Folder 4: 1-6)
  - Military and police, 1990 (Folder 4: 7-9)
  - National Assembly, 1982-1983 (Folder 4: 10)
  - New states, 1981-1983 (Folder 5: 1-3)
  - Nigeria in African press, 1985-1987 (Folder 5: 4-7)
  - Nigeria in the U.S. press, 1978-1983 (Folder 5: 8-9)
  - Nigerian External Telecommunications (NET) fire incident, 1983 (Folder 5: 10-11)
  - Nigerian political history, 1982-1983 (Folder 5: 12)
  - Nigerian political parties, 1981-1983 (Box 5:)
    - Progressive Parties Alliance (PPA), 1982-1983 (Folder 5: 13)
    - National Party of Nigeria (NPN), 1982-1983 (Folder 6: 1-7)
    - Nigerian People's Party (NPP), 1981-1983 (Folder 6: 8-12)
    - Great Nigeria People's Party (GNPP), 1981-1983 (Folder 6: 13)
    - People's Redemption Party (PRP), 1982-1983 (Folder 6: 14-15)
    - Nigeria Advance Party (NAP), 1981-1983 (Folder 6: 16)
    - Party decamping, 1983 (Folder 6: 17)
  - Oil and gas, The Organization of the Petroleum Exporting Countries (OPEC), 1983-1990 (Folder 7: 1-2)
  - Olusegun Obasanjo controversy, 1990 (Folder 7: 3)
  - Opinions on present and future, 1990 (Folder 7: 4-5)
  - People, class; pictures and cartoons, 1990 (Folder 7: 6-7)
  - Police election, 1983 (Folder 7: 8-9)
  - Political culture, 1982-1983 (Folder 7: 10)
  - Political opinions, 1982-1983 (Folder 7: 11)
  - Political transition problem, 1990 (Folder 7: 12)
  - Politics, parties and politicians, 1982-1991 (Folder 7: 13-15)
  - Political violence, 1983 (Folder 7: 16)
  - Politics and police, 1981-1983 (Folder 7: 17)
  - Press and media, 1982-1983 (Folder 7: 18-19)
  - Radical opinions and analyses, 1982-1983 (Folder 7: 20)
  - Religion, 1990 (Folder 7: 21)
  - Religion and politics, 1982-1983 (Folder 8: 1)
  - Religious violence, 1982-1983 (Folder 8: 2)
  - Sociology of the election campaign, 1979-1983 (Box 8-9:)
    - Agricultural and rural development, 1979-1982 (Folder 8: 3)
    - Conduct of election, 1983 (Folder 8: 4-5)
    - Education, literacy campaign, 1982-1983 (Folder 8: 6)
    - Election analyses, 1983 (Folder 8: 7)
    - Election assessment, 1983 (Folder 8: 8)
    - Election disputes, 1983 (Folder 8: 9-10)
    - Election malpractices, 1983 (Folder 8: 11)
    - Election pledges, 1983 (Folder 8: 12)
    - Election prospects and expectations, 1983 (Folder 8: 13)
    - Election results, 1983 (Folder 9: 1)
    - Election tone, 1983 (Folder 9: 2)
    - Election violence, 1983 (Folder 9: 3)
    - Federal Electoral Commission (FEDECO), 1982-1983 (Folder 9: 4-6)
    - Gubernatorial election, 1983 (Folder 9: 7)
    - Future of democracy, 1983 (Folder 9: 8)
    - Legitimacy, 1983 (Folder 9: 9)
    - Police election, 1983 (Folder 9: 10)
    - President Shehu Shagari second term, 1983 (Folder 9: 11)
    - Voters registration, 1983 (Folder 9: 12)
    - Women's role in national development, 1981-1983 (Folder 9: 13)
  - States government political development, 1981-1983 (Box 10-11)
    - Anambra, 1981-1983 (Folder 10: 1)
    - Bauchi, 1981-1983 (Folder 10: 2)
    - Bendel, 1983 (Folder 10: 3)
    - Benue, 1982-1983 (Folder 10: 4)
    - Borno, 1982-1983 (Folder 10: 5)
    - Cross River, 1983 (Folder 10: 6)
    - Gongola, 1981-1983 (Folder 10: 7)
    - Imo, 1981-1983 (Folder 10: 8)
    - Kaduna, 1983 (Folder 10: 9)
    - Kano, 1983 (Folder 10: 10)
    - Kwara, 1982-1983 (Folder 10: 11)
    - Lagos, 1981-1983 (Folder 10: 12)
    - Niger, 1983 (Folder 10: 13)
    - Ogun, 1982-1983 (Folder 10: 14)
    - Ondo, 1982-1983 (Folder 10: 15)
    - Oyo, 1982-1983 (Folder 11: 1)
    - Plateau, 1982-1983 (Folder 11: 2)
    - Rivers, 1981-1983 (Folder 11: 3)
    - Sokoto, 1982-1983 (Folder 11: 4)
  - State of the Nation, 1983 (Folder 11: 5)
  - Structural Adjustment Programs (SAP), implementations and effects, economic policies, 1989-1990 (Folder 11: 6)
  - Students, 1981-1990 (Folder 11: 7)
  - Teachers, 1982-1983 (Folder 11: 8)
  - Trade unions, 1990 (Folder 11: 9)
  - Traditional rulers, 1983-1990 (Folder 11: 10-11)
  - Universities admission policies, bank loans, 1989-1990 (Folder 11: 12)
  - Universities secret cults, 1990 (Folder 11: 13)
  - Women?s health, 1990 (Folder 11: 14)
  - World Bank loans, 1990 (Folder 11: 15)
- Writings and activities file, 1982-2004. (Box 11)
  Consists of research notes, typescripts, materials related to teaching, and conference proceedings.
  - Fulbright Visiting lecturer at Bayero University Kano (BUK), Kano State, Nigeria, 1982-1983. (Folder 11: 16)
    Consists of correspondence, curriculum vitae, notes, and clippings
  - "For a Free and United Democratic Iraq," National United Power Convention (NUPC), Baghdad, 2004 (Folder 11: 17)
    Consists of posters, program, and other printed material in Arabic and English, and currency (dinars) issued by Central Bank of Iraq
  - "Nigeria: Understanding the 1983 Elections," typescript (Folder 11: 18)
  - "Interview with Chief Obafemi Awolowo, National Leader of the Unity Party of Nigeria," 1983 (Folder 11: 19)
  - Notes, 1983 (Folder 11: 20-21)
  - Six 5.25-inch floppy disks labeled book chapter drafts, correspondence, and research material, circa 1987 (Folder 11: 22)